<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Act against unlicensed chaplains, pedagogues, &amp;c. Edinburgh the 12. day of July 1664.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06070</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51784633</idno>
  <idno type="VID">175040</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240898730</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S996A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183807</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">51784633</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06070)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175040)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2710:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Act against unlicensed chaplains, pedagogues, &amp;c. Edinburgh the 12. day of July 1664.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Signed at bottom: Tho. Young.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Education --  Scotland --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Preaching --  Scotland --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Clergy --  Scotland --  Licenses --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Teachers --  Scotland --  Licenses --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Tutors and tutoring --  Scotland --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="genre_form">Broadsides --  Scotland --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:175040:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175040:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175040:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175040:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175040:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175040:3"/>
            <head>ACT AGAINST UNLICENSED CHAPLAINS, PEDAGOGUES, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edinburgh</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 12. <hi>day of July</hi> 1664.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch as it is statute and ordained by the fourth Act of the second Session of our Soveraign Lord's first Parliament, That none be permitted thereafter to preach in publick, or in families, or teach any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick School, or to be Pedagogue to the children of Persons of Quality, without Licence of the Ordinary of the Diocess: And that notwithstanding of the said Act, diverse persons do still continue to preach and keep Schools, and instruct youth, as School-Masters or Pedagogues, without Licence from the Ordinary, as is provided by the said Act: And do thereby the more easily take occasion to instill into the hearts of the Subjects, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of disloyalty and sedition, and of disaffection to the Government of Church and State, as the same is now by Law established. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commission appointed by his Majesty for executing the Lawes in Church affairs, according to the power committed to them: And in prosecution of the foresaid Act of Parliament, and intent thereof, Doth hereby discharge all and whatsoever person or persons here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, to Preach, Lectur, or exhort publickly, or in families, or keep any publick or privat School, or instruct youth as School-Master, or Pedagogue, or ordinarly performe any exercises of Divine Worship in families, or from house to house, without Licence from the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of the Diocess, with certification to the contravieners they shall be proceeded against as seditious persons, and the punishment due to seditious persons, after due conviction of the crime inflicted upon them accordingly: And further, they do hereby discharge all and every of his Majesties Subjects, after publication hereof, to hear any such unlicensed person (he being known to be such) Preach, Lectur, or exhort publickly, or in families; as also to suffer any such Schools to be kept within their bounds, or to entertain any unlicensed person to instruct youth, as Pedagogue, or School-Master, or ordinarily perform exercises of Divine Worship within their familie, after the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> as they will be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable upon their obedience to the Lawes of the Kingdome. And ordain these presents to be published at the Market Crosses of the head-Burghs of the respective Shyres within this Kingdome, that none pretend ignorance of the famine.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Extracted be me <hi>THO. YOUNG.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:175040:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175040:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175040:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175040:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>